<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>VR/AR software and hardware reviews and guides</description>
    <link>
    http://localhost:4000</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Valve Index HMD detailed teardown</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have ever wondered what is inside Valve Index, you might have stumbled upon my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ValveIndex/comments/cpayc5/valve_index_disassembly/&quot;&gt;reddit post from 2019&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve decided to dive into the details of what makes Valve Index great and share my thoughts on tech inside.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/indexteardown</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/indexteardown</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Pico Neo 2 Review</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The first feeling you get when you put on the Pico Neo 2 headset - this is what I hope to get from the Quest 2. It’s not just the lack of screen door effect, or slightly bigger field of view. It is an overall feeling of balance between all the desired features. Would I ever want better screen resolution in autonomous VR? Probably. But not in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/piconeo2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/piconeo2</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Pimax 8k Plus Review</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;First impression which you get when you put on Pimax Vision 8k Plus - wow, now this is a good Pimax headset that can be recommended. And indeed it has multiple improvements that make it a much desired device, compared to my Pimax 5k Plus that I got from Kickstarter last year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/pimax8kplus</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/pimax8kplus</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Huawei VR Glass Review</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;When I heard about the first VR headset from Huawei the size of the normal sunglasses, with capability to work from a phone or a PC and with a SteamVR support from ScarredGhost article, I was excited. Finally we are moving towards consumer devices that do not repel people just from their looks.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/huaweivrglass</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/huaweivrglass</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Let's talk StarVR</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;StarVR is one of the most desirable VR headsets on the market. Partially, it is because we know the team behind it managed to fit 210 degrees of horizontal FOV (Field of View) in a device that is much smaller than Pimax and XTAL headsets. But mostly, because we don’t know much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/starvr</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/starvr</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
